Nicole: Threat status is the current
level of malicious cyber activity and
the potential for damage or disruption
to a computer network or system.
Threat status can include information
regarding attacks from malware or DoS
and will determine whether software
needs to be updated and or extra training
is needed within an organisation or
business to bring everyone up to speed.
The higher the threat status
the greater the threat.
Organisations and businesses may
have their own system for labelling
this by using colours or numbers etc.
Abraham: Threat modelling can be
used to determine a threat status
and identify potential security
threats and any vulnerabilities.
They can also help to determine
how serious the threat is and
what it’s impact would be.
So how do security professionals
determine threat status?
Let’s look at some of the
processes that they can use.
Nicole: Gathering threat intelligence
using OSINT and other reliable sources
to gather information on current threats,
vulnerabilities tools and processes
and the motivations for threat actors.
Keeping up to date with all
assets that are in use within
the business or organisation.
This can help them track down
any flaws or vulnerabilities
that may need to be addressed.
Therefore, it is important to
get alerts if any unauthorised
downloads are made by staff.
Abraham: Keeping up to date with the
ability to mitigate an attack by making
sure the technology is able to counter an
attack, such as upgrading the firewall.
Doing regular risk assessments especially
after expanding any assets, to determine
how attacks may take place and develop
plans for addressing any vulnerabilities.
Nicole: Threat mapping the potential
paths of threats and how attackers
may get from one resource to another.
This can help identify weak
areas and where extra resources
or training may be needed.
After a risk has been assessed
the current threat status is
determined and then recommendations
and actions will take place.
The exact recommendations
will always depend on the
type and level of the threat.